So you all agree that it is
desirable to eliminate bias,
right?
Yeah.
Yes.
So you all think it is possible
to mitigate bias depending
on what actions you take?
Yeah.
So you do think that can make
choices and not just randomly.
More well-grounded
choices are better than
less well-grounded ones,
say, for addressing bias.
I don't think we really
have a choice about things.
People might think that they
do, but they don't really.
We can't choose where we are
born or how smart we are,
and we can't choose if
we get hit by a car.
We think we are making a
choice, but we really aren't.
It's like Sophie said.
It's all just an illusion.
Yeah.
Yeah, you're right.
Randomness doesn't help.
You've convinced me.
Wait.
Did I have a choice, or
was I compelled to agree?
No.
Your neurons told you to agree.
Yes, exactly.
And randomness, a consequence
of a chaotic quantum process,
just makes what we
do not predictable
but doesn't mean that
we choose what we do.
Right.
Well, you have a choice whether
you're going to be biased
or not.
Mhm.
Indeed.
It does seem that
judgments involve choice.
But Alyssa, if you were
given the full understanding
of a situation, wouldn't you
always take the best action?
Yeah, of course.
No.
You can't really choose whether
anything is better or worse.
It's all just a value judgment.
You may be compelled to
do something by others,
but you never really
freely choose.
Do you really believe
that, or are you
just playing devil's advocate?
OK.
A little of both.
But even if I am just
playing devil's advocate,
what's wrong with
what I'm saying?
What's wrong is that your model
of human life is inadequate.
It doesn't describe
what it really is.
We're not just some balls
moving around deterministically
with random noise interspersed
like a term in a Langevin
equation.
Isn't that true,
Professor Muller?
What a great discussion this is.
Sounds like you had
a much better spring
break discussing these questions
than going to the beach.
[CHUCKLES]
I think you're on the
right track, Sophie.
Funny.
Coincidentally, that's
my first name too.
At any rate, you have
unveiled a great tension
in modern science.
We are brought up to think
that modern science is the way
to describe the
world, but it seems
inadequate to
describe human things.
Ethical questions cannot be
reducible to mathematics--
similar to justice and
beauty, hope and suffering,
and, for that
matter, even truth.
Yes, Glenda.
Aren't those things even more
important than modern science?
I would say so.
No.
Those things are
arbitrary or a matter
of individual's interests--
what's in it for them.
That's the way to look
at them scientifically.
Bias exists because people
have conflicting interests.
Sure, if you look at it
purely scientifically,
but interest alone cannot
be adequate since people are
willing to sacrifice interests
for passions and, more
importantly, for things
beyond themselves.
At any rate, do most
of us really know
all of our interests?
We all have preferences that
go far beyond interests.
Perhaps we can say at best that
those interests are intertwined
with different
approaches to the world.
Besides, aren't the most
boring people the ones who say,
I'm right, and, even if one
can never make value judgments,
I have my own values
and I stick with them?
[CHUCKLES] Yeah, these are
the most irritating and boring
people.
So, now let's dig down a bit
more into the mathematics
of AI and the sorting problem.
Perhaps it's best to start
with a specific example.
What's the reason for the
bias in facial recognition
that we discussed
a little while ago?
A biased training set due
to historical inequity.
OK.
So one of the issues
is the training set.
The other issue
is the algorithm,
including its hyperparameters,
all leading to how
the classification is done.
This is why different algorithms
give different error rates
using the same training data.
Anything else?
Right.
So those are the two key issues.
However, within the
choice of algorithm,
there is the problem
with classification.
Let me project
this data set, here
with points in red and blue.
You have many choices for
putting the dividing surface.
But what if we
choose the wrong one?
Some of the data may be
misclassified, won't it?
You mean like this?
Yes, exactly.
So how do you choose the
right line ahead of time?
That is a problem.
It could be even worse if
your data set looks like this.
But then we don't have
to stick with lines.
Why don't you draw
a curve around them?
Like this?
Yes, exactly.
Now you've classified
them all perfectly.
Well, wait a second.
If you do that, it works
for the training set,
but it may not work for
any additional data sets.
In fact, it might be
even worse than the lines
because you're overfitting
to the training data.
Do you mean like this?
Yeah.
That doesn't work.
Oh, yes.
I see it.
Exactly.
Remember this is a sorting
algorithm, here in two
dimensions with two descriptors,
thus it is quite limited.
But even if you do it in a very
large number of dimensions with
a very large number
of descriptors,
you are still projecting
a complicated system--
shall we say a natural system--
onto an artificial
mathematical construct
that necessarily leaves
much out of the description.
Or if you want to stay in
the realm of mathematics,
you could say that due to
a necessary incomplete set
of descriptors you
were fitting noise.
This allows you to get a perfect
fit for your training set,
but then you have an even
worse fit for your data set
moving forward.
Patch.
In other words, we
have to accept the fact
that there will be errors.
But at least we could distribute
the errors evenly among groups.
That is what Alyssa said before.
We can try, but
then I'm worried we
won't include all the groups.
Even if we could, there'll
be errors in the errors.
Unless we have a very,
very large training
set, which practically
we never have,
we won't be able to do that.
Yes.
The training set would
have to incorporate
all the data in the world.
You know, that
reminds me of a story
I once heard, I think from
a South American writer,
where someone makes a one-to-one
scale map of their country
with all the details included.
[CHUCKLES]
Ha, ha.
Well, I grant the problem.
But then what do we do?
We all agree that we
need to eliminate bias,
but it seems so hard.
What if we could at least
have a very extensive model
that for all practical purposes
captures a given situation?
Which I guess is
actually impossible
because it would require a
complete and accurate model
of all the objects
in the whole world.
Yes.
As engineers, we can at
least work to do that.
If the model is extensive
enough, we can eliminate bias.
But then we'd be eliminating any
choice that we might have had.
We would be controlled
by an algorithm.
That sounds-- that
sounds tyrannical.
Indeed.
Mathematization of human
things distorts them so much
that they become something
which they are not.
This is actually the
utilitarian approach.
Human things like joy, anger,
justice, honor, beauty,
and happiness are really
not mathematizable.
We lose all of what
is important in them
when we mathematize them.
We could in principle try to
do so and therein transform
human reality.
Glenda.
That doesn't sound appealing.
It sounds dreadful.
Yeah, that wouldn't be good.
But we can at least do
it partially, can't we?
Yes.
Maybe that would
be a good solution.
Yes.
Even if those human
things cannot be described
by mathematics, it is still the
only rigorous way to understand
the world.
I'm not so sure anymore, but
the bias is in the data set,
and it is in the algorithms.
So we must be able to adjust
our models to solve the problem.
Mustn't we?
Well, consider this-- our
recognition of the problem
of bias is not mathematical.
Mathematics comes only
after such recognition.
Mathematics is something
we impose on our broader
understanding of the world.
We can use it to develop
models, but they will always
be just that, models
which are necessarily
incomplete descriptions.
I see what you're
saying, I think.
Sophie.
But AI is based on mathematics.
So we have to fix this
problem in the algorithms
via fixing the algorithms, i.e.
by using mathematics.
Don't we?
Well, we can think
of things this way,
but that will lead us
to a double whammy.
We cannot develop a
non-arbitrary definition
of the criteria for the
training set, and, two,
we cannot develop a
non-arbitrary definition
of the error target for
the sorting algorithm.
Well, I knew that we
were at an impasse,
but I didn't think it
was this big of one.
Professor, your
class has made us
more stuck than we were before.
So, what do we do?
Is there another way?
Indeed, Glenda, there is that.
It requires a reconsideration of
our concerns and of the issue.